<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divers remarkable passages concerning the originall and progresse of the present great action in Essex: and the reason of seizing on the Lord Capel's sonne. Expressed in a letter to a retired gentleman, from his friend in London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81563</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871782</idno>
  <idno type="VID">161995</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240947769</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E453_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22542</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871782</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99871782e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81563)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161995)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 72:E453[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divers remarkable passages concerning the originall and progresse of the present great action in Essex: and the reason of seizing on the Lord Capel's sonne. Expressed in a letter to a retired gentleman, from his friend in London.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Includes errata.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Essex (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161995:1"/>
            <p>Divers Remarkable PASSAGES <hi>CONCERNING</hi> The Originall and Progresse of the present great Action in <hi>ESSEX: AND</hi> The reason of seizing on the Lord <hi>CAPEL'S</hi> Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Expressed in a Letter to a retired Gentleman, from his friend in</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:161995:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161995:2"/>
            <head>Diverse remarkable Passages concerning the Originall, and Progresse of the present great <hi>Action</hi> in <hi>Essex</hi> and the reason of Seazing on the Lord <hi>Capells</hi> Son.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our great retirednesse I see, is accompanyed with many sad thoughts, for the present condition of your native Country; &amp; though you are not a man of <hi>Action</hi> in these unhappy troubles, yet I perceive you are a person of great <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> for the removall of them: You desire to know of me, the Originall of the present distraction in <hi>Essex,</hi> because I live here in the City, whither all the News comes; and have some good acquaintance in that County: You desire also, to understand the truth of that Act (which your selfe and Lady apprehends so barbarons) in seizing on the Lord <hi>Capells</hi> son, the manner and reason of it, and how people in the City doe censure the same. Sir, I know the Honour is great, and the Affection strong, which both you, and your Lady bear to that Noble Lord, (unto whose Family you have a neere relation.) I also have much reverence in my heart towards him, for that great Loyalty &amp; Faithfulnesse in him to his King and Country; which I think all men must confesse to be fully manifest by his magnanimous deportment in his present ingagement, though there had been no former proofes of it: Wherefore I shall, in this particular which concerneth him and his son, as also in the other, satisfie your desires as well as I am able, (though I doubt not but some others might have done it better) by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161995:3"/>giving you that historicall relation of the whole businesse, which from the testimony of severall men I have industriously learned, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be the truth. And 'tis this.</p>
            <p>The County of <hi>Essex</hi> having, in an humble way Petitioned the two Houses for a Treaty with the King; a disbanding the Army, and a removeall of their greivances; and received back a slight and unsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying Answer, as they apprehended: resolved to renew their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests in the same submissive manner and way as before: but obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by that barbarous entertainment which their neighbours of <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey</hi> met withall; that those, whom they were to make their addresses unto at <hi>Westminster,</hi> were worse spirited, and more cruelly disposed then ever <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the Tyrant of <hi>Aegypt</hi> was, who did not set his men of War to <hi>Kill, Slay, and Destroy</hi> the Afflicted <hi>Iraelites,</hi> when they put up their prayers to be eased of their Burdens: And percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving withall, (by a <hi>crosse Petition</hi> then in hand, (and with diligence promoted by the Sectaries of the County) that there was a storme a rising against themselves, for giving example to those of <hi>Surry</hi> and others, in supplicating for such things as they have done: they thought it necessary and meet to consult speedily about their own defence; and to this purpose, convened at <hi>Chelmesford;</hi> where they found one Sir <hi>William Massam,</hi> a man whom (in their good opinion) they had Honoured to be Knight of their Shire; together with 4 more Parliament men, and diverse <hi>Committee-men</hi> in consultation to raise divisions in the County, &amp; oppositions against those who were for the peace and safety thereof: with whom they did expostulate about the said turbulent and crosse Petition, which (they said) was counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced and promoted by them: shewing them diverse warrants sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed by some of their hands, for the speedy dispersion of it: but they in their confusion of spirit (notwithstanding the evidence) were pleased to deny the same; whereat the people were very much moved against them (the untruth being so clearly manifest to the face of the whole County.) And they were exasperated further, by that which they heard then, and there attested by one Major <hi>Wilmore,</hi> an honest and resolute Gentleman of the County, viz. that himself, and diverse other sufficient witnesses had lately heard a Parliament man protest, and say, <hi>That if there were an</hi> 100. <hi>Barrells of Powder under the Parliament House, and a traine layed, and a match ready to give fire, he would rather be blowne up, then yeild to a Treaty with the King:</hi> And this was uttered by him, as if it were the sense of all the then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161995:3"/>prevailing party in the Houses: whereby the Country apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the said faction were resolved directly upon the Kings ruine, in that they would rather choose a sudden destruction, then come to the light, whereby their deeds might be made manifest, which (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by this their shinesse) would (in their own thoughts) be but an usher to a more shamefull down-fall, if His Majesties innocency and righteousnesse so highly wronged and abused should come to be but cleerly viewed by His People.</p>
            <p>And then further yet, some of the Country had understood; How another Parliament man also, had discovered the sense and purpose of the House, to be <hi>in no hand to comply with the King,</hi> though it was believed, and confessed, that in regard of His Majesties disposition and condition, He both could, and would pardon them: <hi>For should there be such a Compliance, and His Majesty suffered to speak, and so businesse be discussed before the People, the Kingdome</hi> (said He) <hi>would never suffer the Militia to continue any longer in our hands, and we being bereft of power to cause awe, and dread, should be torne in peices,</hi> (soil. for what they had done) <hi>or at least should live in such contempt and scorne, that death would be better unto us, then such a life:</hi> And therefore, though he confessed it was believed also, (in regard of the great change in peoples hearts) that the King and His Party would get the better in the end; <hi>yet</hi> (sayes he) <hi>we are resolved before that time come, to make the Land and Kingdome not worth His owning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this evill expression also, having come to the ears of many <hi>Essex</hi> men there present, it spake to their hearts, that the intentions of those who call themselves the <hi>Parliament,</hi> was (in defence of their own Tyranny and justice) to hazard the totall ruine of their King and Country.</p>
            <p>These, and such like considerations, did at that time much stirre the mindes of the people: And yet, by the advise of some of the chiefe and more discreet, amongst them; they propounded to those Members of Parliament there present, the dangers and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities which they were in; requesting them to be meanes for them to the Parliament, that the Country might now at length be free from taxes, and quartring Souldiers; and put into a defensive posture, under officers of their owne choice, whom they may confide in; that so they might upon occasion, be both able and ready to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the same: (which was no more then these very Parliament men themselves had moved them to petition for, six years agoe, when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161995:4"/>there was no such imminent or visible danger as was now apparent.) This request so modest and reasonable, was thought would easily have been furthered by those who were intrusted for the Countries good; but they, (notwithstanding their duty and engagement) retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a slight Answer unto the people; who, when they heard the same read, cryed out with one voice, no Answer, no Answer; which notwithstanding, (being written in a paper) was thrown down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them in a carelesse way, as all the Answer they must look for; and apprehended by the people to be so done in contempt and scorne of them all: whereupon they violently rushed up staires, and inclosed the said Parliament men, together with the Committee in their Chamber, and set a guard upon them.</p>
            <p>Yet after this, all the Parl. men were released (except <hi>Massam</hi>) and sent (upon their promise of returne) with those their desires unto the Parliament: and diverse of the Committee-men, as one M. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and one M. <hi>Young,</hi> who were known to be men of a moderate temper, and not mischievous, were freely let out, and permitted to goe to their owne homes. And had not the peevish and evill dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of unworthy Sir <hi>William Massam</hi> towards his Country, who had so highly honoured him, been so notorious to all; in is most probable that he also had been afforded like favour with the rest. But when he was moved to joyne with the Country in the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their righteous and reasonable desires: He Answered, that <hi>it was not just to move him, being a prisoner, unto any thing of that nature, or to require ought of him, till he were at liberty, for it was no other then a plaine inforcement upon his Conscience,</hi> while he was in that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; complaining withall, <hi>what a great misery it was to be a prisoner and restrained of freedome.</hi> Whereunto, Sir <hi>William Martin,</hi> a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee man that was under the same restraint with him, Replyed, <hi>You are sensible of this as a misery, now tis your own case, only two dayes, but you have been no whit sensible of it, as tis the Kings case, whom you have kept in prison well nigh two yeares.</hi> And you think it an unjust en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement upon <hi>your Conscience to be moved to joyne with your Country in a matter whereunto you are bound in duty: only because you are under restraint: What injustice then have you shewn, in urging the King, as you have done, to yield His consent to so many unreasonable things against His Honour, Judgement, and Conscience, throughout the whole time of His Imprisonment?</hi> This reply comming to the knowledge and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of Sir <hi>Charles Lucas,</hi> he presently with the liking of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161995:4"/>Country, set the said Sir <hi>Willam Martin</hi> at Liberty, because (as he told him) he perceived by that his expression, that he <hi>had some true love in his heart unto the King:</hi> Whereby is inferred, that the Kings Friends desire to have none under restraint, but enemies to their King and Country, who are, and would be mischievous to both, white they be at liberty.</p>
            <p>But I proceed: The Parliament <hi>Members,</hi> who were sent with the Counties desires to the <hi>Houses,</hi> upon their paroll, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of returne, (accounting it (as seemed) against the Honour and Priviledge of Parliament to keep their word) returned no more; but sent down the promise of an Ordinance of Indempnity to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if they would (acknowledging themselves in a fault) goe every man to his own home, and release their Prisoners. Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> (who had been called, and sent for thither by the Centlemen of the County) might also for his own person, be included in the same Ordinance: But for the Earl of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and those men of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>London</hi> which came with him, must be all left to <hi>Parliament mercy.</hi> This Act or promise of Indempnity was accepted of by many, and the rather, because of the misfortune of the <hi>Kentish</hi> forces, the noise whereof, came at that time in the highest tiune to this Countries eares, to its great disadvantage.</p>
            <p>But diverse others of the Gentry and Yeomanry, who had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter observed that little of faith and truth, which had ever yet been found in Parliament promises; made present choice of the Noble <hi>Lucas</hi> for their Generall; who was the rather induced to take the Charge upon him, for the love which he bore to his native County; &amp; also in pitty and commiseration to those thousands of Souls; which were otherwise to be left unto Parliament mercy; (from which, as from the extreamest cruelty, <hi>good Lord deliver us.</hi>) Now this pious and worthy Act of Sir <hi>Charles,</hi> as it hath knit the hearts of all those, and many others to him, in so strong a tie of love, that nothing but death shall unloose: so doubt but the Almighty God (by wose grace he dit it) doth and will so favourably approve of the same, that (we hope) his divine blessing shall attend him in all his publick undertakings.</p>
            <p>For we had experience once already of Gods aide and blessing in a like case, <hi>viz.</hi> when that truly valiant and religious Gentleman the now Lord <hi>Hopton,</hi> was with other persons of great honour and quality, at the beginning of these troubles, to take Ship for <hi>Wales.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161995:5"/>at <hi>Minehead</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> and wanting boates to transport all their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, were forced to leave some hundreds behinde on shore, who would be necessitated to fall into the hands of the Enemies: But this most worthy man looking back from the Ship, his bowels stirred towards them: whereupon he commands himself to be carryed back unto them; and tels them, Gentlemen, <hi>it grieves me to leave you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde us, who have thus far ventured your selves with us in this righteous Cause: I am therefore returned to partake of your fortune, and am resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Gods Grace, to adventure my life with you:</hi> Which most noble and Christian Act God was so well pleased with, that he knit the Soudiers hearts most firmly to him, and made him successefull, even to admiration in the <hi>West</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> and it will be confessed of all, that no one Army since these Wars begun, was more beloved of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where they came, more prosperous for the King, and more ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to His Cause, then that was, while the said Lord <hi>Hopton,</hi> and those gallant <hi>Cornish</hi> Gentry His Assistants did Command the same. Now we cannot build our faith in God, concerning our present case, (which is of a like nature to that) upon a better foundation then such former experience: God that aided the renowned and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passionate <hi>Hopton;</hi> will also prosper the Noble and mercifull <hi>Lucas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to returne to our matter, about this time the crafty Enemy considering the Christian constancy, and unshakable Loyalty of that true Lover of His King and Country, the Lord <hi>Capell.</hi> And know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his place of Residence, was not far distant from <hi>Essex:</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending by that experience they had of him, that his stout and gallant spirit disdain'd to stoop to Compound with Rebels for the Estate, which God, his Auncestors, and the Laws of the Land had given, and settled upon him; and the conceiving by his carriage towards them, that he was carelesse to enjoy his owne Land, so long as the King was without His Crown; concluded to send speedily for him, and to clap him up close prisoner, and so prevent that comfort and encouragement, which his being at Liberty might afford to the Kings Friends in <hi>Essex.</hi> But his Lordship having private notice of these purposes against him, though the <hi>Essex</hi> businesse was yet excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding raw in his apprehension, and (as himself confessed to a friend of his) not ripe enough for him to engage his person in: yet considering the uselesse condition he was sure to be shortly in, by being a Prisoner, conceiving that the notice he had thereof before hand
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161995:5"/>might be from a speciall providence to thrust him forth unto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent service; and finding his Affections most strong and sincere for his Kings enlargement, and his Countries freedome: He resolved to adventure himself, (though against his judgement, in regard of the immaturity of the enterprize) and to <hi>trust God wholly with the successe;</hi> it was his own expression to his friend in private, who told it me; which, when I heard, I thought presently of that speech of <hi>David,</hi> when he went out to fight the <hi>Lords Battaile against the uncircumcised Philistims, I goe forth</hi> (saith he) <hi>in the name or strength only of the Lord of Hosts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon these grounds, this Nobleman removed himself to <hi>Chel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misford,</hi> leaving his pious and dear Lady great with child, and his particular Affaires (of great concernment then in Agitation) to Gods sole protection and disposall, not so much as ordering (though some suggested the motion) that his eldest son should be conveyed to some private concealment; for himself being full of candour, noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and humanity, could not (surely) conceive it possible, that any who wore the shapes of men, and were named Christians, or called Gentlemen, would offer, or suffer to be offered, any thing unworthy to such a Lady as his was, and in her condition; or to any of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and harmlesse Children: nay, he might rather think, that that for the Name sake, and honour of Parliament, they who were now so called, would (as they were bound) protect them from wrongs and incivilities.</p>
            <p>After his Lordships arrivall at <hi>Chelmisford,</hi> (which was to the great rejoycing of all those Loyal hearts) the forces there removed within 2 dayes (by reason haply of the Enemies suddain &amp; speedy approach) to <hi>Braintry,</hi> and from thence next day, towards <hi>Colchester,</hi> (carrying Sir <hi>William Massam,</hi> and the rest of the Committee with them, using them with all civility and gentlenesse;) and they march'd with their Army through the Country in that orderly and unblameable way and manner, as was to all mens admiration; only at <hi>Earls Colne,</hi> some of the foolish townsmen by the excitation of one <hi>Josseline</hi> (a factious Priest) stood with their Guns and Musquets to oppose them, which was a sufficient provocation unto them to plunder the Town, had they had any such disposition; they urged no mans person to joyne with them, but accepted only of those that offered their voluntary service. Indeed their fairnesse and civill behaviour did the more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently appear, by the outragious and contrary demeanour of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161995:6"/>
               <hi>Fairfax's</hi> men, who in a sort pursued them, forcing the Country against their wills to joyne with them; and fetching their provision daily from them without paying any thing for the same; and plundring those, who by evill neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours were noted to them, to be of a different judgement and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Essex</hi> forces had not been in <hi>Cholchester</hi> 24 houres, before the enemy made a most feirce and furious assault upon them with sword and fire; confidently presuming, in regard of his former suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses and present strength, and the apprehended weaknesse of the Town, and suddaine feares or disaffections of the inhabitants that he should that night make an end of the businesse.</p>
            <p>But <hi>on the mount the Lord was seen;</hi> who appeared wonderfully in the behalf of his assaulted people, for he rebuked the enemy very sharply; and gave them by this despised handfull, the greatest check that since the beginning of the Wars they had received: I take no pleasure to say how many hundreds of them were there slaine, and how many most miserably wounded; I am an <hi>Englishman,</hi> and my heart bleeds to heare or speak of the numbers of my slaughtered Country-men: indeed the Enemy hath taken most speciall and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning courses to conceal his losses from the peoples knowledge; But I shall leave the discovery thereof to other pens, onely this I must observe, (as many others doe beside my self;) Generall <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his Army went into <hi>Essex</hi> with the highest scorne and contempt of those, whom they were to oppose, and with the greatest purposes of cruelty against them, as could be imagined, threatning to swallow them up at a bit, and (as they said) <hi>to cut the Calves throats presently:</hi> And it must be confessed to Gods sole glory, that it was beyond the expectation or faith of man, that the Royall party in the Town should have been able (all things considered) to have done the tenth part of those things which they have done since they went thither: but God, who is never failing unto men in distresse, when they be in righteous wayes, and doe repose their trust in him, hath wrought all their works for them even to admiration, (as hereafter I hope (when we have the full relation) shall be declared to the Almighties praise) and in the mean time let all that wish happinesse to their King and Country, adore the Lord for his goodnesse already manifested, and fervently supplicate his divine Majesty for his further protection and assistance, to those loyall and good men, who in defence of their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161995:6"/>Religion, Laws and Country, are now in Arms in that town of <hi>Cholchester.</hi> I now proceed to your other particular.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Massam</hi> the Parliament man, finding it now more pleasant to send others to the Wars, then to be there himself; though but as a spectator or looker on, and fearing (as seemed) in regard of his black and guilty soul, that every shot which his friends without let flie against the Town, would beat down some house about his head; wanting also that state and service, that variety of wine, and plenty of dainties in this besieged place which he was wont to abound in at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and so thinking himselfe in a lesse glorious condition here then there, and that he had not altogether so much respect and crowching unto, (though he wants for no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries which the Town can afford;) thought it his wisdome to cry before he was hurt, and as some creatures (we know) will make a greater noise, if they fear but touching, then sheep will doe, when shorne or slaughtred; so did he whine and keep adoe, sending forth pitifull complaints, by privy messages to his Brethren at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and their Master the <hi>Generall;</hi> to the end (as appeared by the event) that some of the Wives, Chidren, or friends of those who had him in Bondage, might be seized on as prisoners, to be given in exchange for him: This motion or intimation was presently relished by the prevailing Faction in the House of Commons, who had (as it seemes) resolved now to put off Humanity as well as Loyalty; and to leave off to be Gentlemen as well as Christians: And therefore they set themselves presently about the Businesse: amongst whom, it was propounded and urged in a very earnest manner, (as I head) by one <hi>Gurdon</hi> of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> and <hi>Henry Mildmay</hi> of <hi>Essex,</hi> (an unworthy Kinsman of the Lord <hi>Capell</hi>) that the Lady of the said Lord) being great with child) should be sent to the Head-quarters, and there be dealt withall as should seeme good to their Generall; but this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not allowed of by the House, because it would speak them to be in too too desperate a condition, in that sort, to take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of shewing Cruelty to the person of a great-bellied Woman: But it was concluded against her eldest Son, a Gentleman of some 16 years of Age to send him. Now some say, that the Generall himself sent for him, by a first and second Message, being (as they say) very angry with God for giving such a check to his boysterous procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and then the losse of his Treasure (some 80000 l. as is reported)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161995:7"/>at <hi>Pomfret</hi> Castle came to his ears about that time, which did not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle heighten his discontent and fury, and therefore he longed to be in Action, and to have such in his power, whom he thought he could master: thus some doe censure, though others indeed do affirme for him, that he is more a Souldier, then to make so unmanly a request, or indeed to approve of so barbarous an Act; (and they say too, that when he saw the young Gentleman, he was offended (or seemed at least so to be) at those that sent him.) But however, this noble youth was by Order of Parliament seized upon, and rent from the presence of his tender Mother, which sudden &amp; unexpected inhumanity caused her (as is said) to fall into present travaile of Child-birth, to the great hazard of her life; though the mercifull God, by his mighty power (through he strength of faith) hath yet upheld her Spirit, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd her in being.</p>
            <p>Her Ladiship hereupon (as their own books tell us) sent a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the House of Lords in the behalf of her Son, <hi>who is</hi> (say they) <hi>apprehended, and sent down to the Generall, to be used in the same condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Committee of</hi> Essex <hi>are with the Enemy; and desiring she may have such satisfaction herein, as may be for the Justice and Honour of Parliament.</hi> For so (indeed) they call themselves, and for the Honour of that they pretend to stand: The Lords recommended the said Petition to the Commons: (for to doe them right, they had (I head) so much Honour left, as to abhor the fact even from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.) Now the Commons either being ignorant what this <hi>Honour and Justice of Parliament</hi> was, or else not daring to interpret what it ought to be, <hi>Ordered hereupon</hi> (saies their perfect Diurnall) <hi>that a Letter should be written from the House to the Lord Generall</hi> Fairfax, <hi>with the Petition of the said Lady</hi> Capell <hi>therein, and that his Lordship be desired to doe therein, as may be for the Justice and Honour of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> leaving it to him (being a Sword-man) to determine what that is now grown to be.</p>
            <p>He receiving the same, sent his Letter into <hi>Colchester,</hi> signifying (sayes their Book) that <hi>the Parliament being sensible of their seizing on Sir</hi> William Massam, <hi>and others of the Committee, (not being Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Warre) had sent downe the Lord</hi> Capel's <hi>sonne, with others, that he might be sent in exchange for Sir</hi> William Massam.</p>
            <p>In which Tender is apprehended to be, as little of Justice, as valour, and as little of Piety and Honesty, as of either the other two: For people argue thus.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:161995:7"/>
            <p> Sir <hi>William Massam</hi> (they say) is a Malefactor, a mischievous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, old in wickednesse: and though no Prisoner of War, yet a prime Author of it, yea the principall man that raised or caused the present War in the County of <hi>Essex:</hi> Whereas Master <hi>Capell</hi> is a young Gentleman, of a pure and candid spirit, of a sweet and gracious dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, who knowes no evill, nor ever did, or intended hurt to the County of <hi>Essex,</hi> or to any creature.</p>
            <p>Againe, Sir <hi>William Massam</hi> (they say) was apprehended for his faults, by those whose Servant he was, and to whom he was to give an account for his ill discharge of the trust reposed in him: having lately before, renounced the same, disclaiming to performe his duty any longer, by publishing to the world (with the rest of his fellowes) that <hi>they would treat no more with the King,</hi> (to which they were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen, and appointed by their Counties.) Yea, and he was seized upon too (as tis observed) while he was in the very act of sin, plotting to raise strife in his Country, having for seven yeeres together, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to impoverish its wealth, and to worke its ruine. Yea and a few dayes before, he had on the publique Bench used threatning ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions to those of the same, who promoted a Petition for the Kings safety and honour, and for the Kingdomes peace, and had ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Parliament to send downe Souldiers to inslave the same: Now no such things could be laid to the charge of young Mr. <hi>Capell,</hi> that he should be judged meet to be put into the scale with such a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. His onely faults are his Parents vertues, and his owne innocence, and for these he was taken Prisoner in his Fathers house, where he was at his Study, by those who had no Authority over him, to whom he had no relation at all; nor had ever done them the least evill.</p>
            <p>Besides, Sir <hi>Will: Massam</hi> (as they who know him say) is, as of no such worth, so of no such great birth, or fortunes, as to be weighed in the Ballance with this Spark of Honour, who is Heire to a great Estate, of a noble and unspotted Family: and therefore that this little Gentleman should be thus valued or offered in exchange, for that other thing who is so little of a Gentleman, is generally concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be very unjust, ridiculous, and unworthy.</p>
            <p>Yea and father yet, the world observes and sayes, that if there was any error committed in the seizing upon Sir <hi>William Massam,</hi> and his fellows, it was committed by the Inhabitants and people of <hi>Essex</hi> six dayes before the Lord <hi>Capels</hi> comming amongst them, without his knowledge, or privity: nor was he the Generall of <hi>Essex</hi> men after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161995:8"/>onely he came to them as a friend to lend them his assistance, as they appeared for the liberty of the King and the Law: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that his Child should be imprisoned, his Lady affrighted, and threatned, or himselfe any way damnified for that act of <hi>Essex</hi> men, is a thing so ignominious and highly base, that all people (but the Actors) cry open shame upon it.</p>
            <p>And indeed how did <hi>William of Nassaw</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie, inveigh against the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> taxing him of Barbarous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, Inhumanity, and Ignoblenesse, for seizing upon his Son a Youth, and at Schoole, when he could not reach himselfe? And how did the whole Christian world then, concur with that Prince, in condemning the said King, for that unkingly and unsoldierly act: for though the Father had revolted from his due obedience, yet to punish him in his child, to take revenge upon one that was innocent, shewed rather pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionate fury then discretion; and cowardly basenesse, then any thing else. But indeed, this act of Generall <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his Parliament. though the same in kind, with that of the <hi>Spanish</hi> King, yet in regard of the circumstances is many degrees more injust and vile: For the Father of this noble Youth had not revolted from any obedience to them, for he never acknowledged any due unto them since they revolted from their Soveraigne; but because they cannot yet be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on him, for his piety and faithfulnesse to his King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; therefore they will wreak their spleen upon his Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and because they cannot get guilty persons to exchange for Traitors, they will offer innocents, and threaten to expose such to slaughter.</p>
            <p>But doubtlesse, Generall <hi>Fairfax</hi> fancied as much pusilanimity in the Father of this young Gentleman (when he sent his fore-named letter into <hi>Colchester</hi>) as would (perhaps) have appeared in his own poor spirited selfe, in a case of like nature; and that he was as unable to distinguish Gold from Drosse as he; but he was quickly resolved on the contrary: for that Heroick Lord returnes his answer (as their own book saies) that very evening in these words. 1. <hi>That he conceived it inhamane,</hi> (viz. in the Enemies to doe as they had done.) 2. <hi>That if all the Committee had been offered for his son,</hi> (viz. by those of his own party) <hi>he would have disdained the motion.</hi> 3. <hi>That he joyed to see any of his, if no other way, yet by their sufferings to pay the duty they owe to their King, and the known Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I know you cannot forbear (at the reading of this) to cry out
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161995:8"/>as many others have done: O truly noble and Christian spirit! O magnanimous expression of perfect Loyalty, worthy indeed to be written in golden Letters, and transmitted to posterity for an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting patterne of instruction, and speciall meanes of inspiration! And I think you will hope (as I doe) that since God doth give us such speciall gages of his love and mercy, (as men of such high cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and honour are) we may with comfort and confidence conclude, that he hath not yet left off to intend good to this poor Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Indeed 'tis fancyed by a great many, that the Heroick Answer of this Nobleman, together with the consideration of the unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Act so generally resented and cryed out upon, will work so upon the spirits of the Agents, that for pure shame at least, they will send back the young Gentleman, and endeavour, by some speciall respect to that Famliy, to lessen the deformity of this so op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious inhumanity; though these be some, I confesse (who know them well) that are of a contrary opinion: but let me assure you 'tis the judgment of wise men, that the Generall and House of Commons could not have done a more imprudent Act to their own disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage then this was, and is like to be, so evilly 'tis apprehended by all sorts of people.</p>
            <p>And thus (noble Sir) I have given what satisfaction I am able to your self and Lady, in the particulars you write about. What the issue of <hi>Colchester</hi> busines will yet be, is not evident, many reports we have, that the Enemy which lies before it, hath lost many hundreds if not some thousands of men, surely aboundance most lamentably wounded, are daily sent to <hi>London</hi> from him: Tis much observed how God hath opposed and resisted the Pride of the Army, for if words doe manifest thoughts, and threats intentions; never any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook a businesse with more presumption of heart, and cruelty of spirit then they did this of <hi>Essex:</hi> But how hath the Heavens and Stars in their courses seemed to fight against them, since they besieged that despised place; for indeed, though this judgement of Raine hath been upon us all, and threatens a generall calamity to ensue, (which indeed we have all deserved) yet it cannot be denyed, but they have been most specially detrimented in their designe, by those bottles of Heaven, which God hath powered out upon them in their Trenches, whereby their Souldiers are much impaired in their healths, besides those wounds which they receive daily from the defendants, whom they thought they had taken in a trap: God is stronger
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161995:9"/>then the <hi>Militia,</hi> nor doth he care for the Anger of man; he hath abated the strength of this great Generall, and his Forces; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruite, which the unwilling Country are made to help forward their own destruction, and driven on (they say) as <hi>Turkish</hi> Slaves are, to be food for the Bullet: Provisions are commanded from them beside to be brought in <hi>gratis,</hi> ready dressed to the Army daily; one Town I head, (within 12 miles of them) is at 36 l. the week for Food for them; and so are all others proportionably charged to the same purpose. yea, and from the Inhabitants of that County also money must be raised (according to Ordinance) to pay their Souldiers their wages, who by their Horses, and other wayes, doe extreamely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the Corne and Fruites there, which fore-speaks a most sad and speedy famine shortly: And more then this, 'tis Ordered by the House of Commons, that 4500 l. more be raised in that County, for advancing two Troops and a company of Dragoones for the service of it: for so it must be called, though it be evident enough, that 'tis, &amp; will be for the ruine of it. Yea, and it must be beleevd too, that this, with all its present miseries are for its good, and that the continuance of them, is for its preservation.</p>
            <p>And this (as most men observe) is that County which hath been so constantly faithfull to the Parliament from the very beginning, and so forward in affording assistance on all occasions: now it is apparent what the reward and wages is, which it must be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with, in lieu of all its love, service and monies: nor can it be charged to have offered any other way, then by groaning under its burdens, and sighing forth its petitions, in an humble way for peace and quiet.</p>
            <p>But in very deed, there was (as wise and good men apprehend) more of modesty and fairnesse in that course which this Country took to manifest their greivances, then there was of justice and Courage; and tis believed that the miseries now upon it, are permitted of God as a just punishment, for making those their Addresses in so submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive a way, as that was by Petition: After the House of Commons had declared to the world, <hi>that they would make no more Addresses to the King.</hi> They ought rather, when they heard this, to have been an example, &amp; led the way unto the whole Kingdome, in re-calling their Knights and Burgesses then in Petitioning to them; and have gone up rather with Swords in their hands, then Papers, to them, who had disclaimed to Treat with the King (being honoured with the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161995:9"/>trust of <hi>Parliament men</hi> only to that end &amp; purpose) then in petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any more unto them. For indeed, after they had discovered themselves so far, it was the duty of all men to have forborn; yea, and abhord to have given any further respects unto them: Which, because they did not, therefore are they (as tis beleeved) by Gods permission and providence thus afflicted and tormented.</p>
            <p>And so the Massacre that was made upon <hi>Surry</hi> men, did (in respect of God) betide them justly, for following in the same way as these of <hi>Essex</hi> had done. And <hi>Kent</hi> in like manner, for but endeavouring &amp; purposing to tread in those steps, hath in some sort smarted already, and are terribly threatned to be humbled further, even unto beggery and bondage, by these <hi>Flagella Dei,</hi> when their present imployments are a little over: And 'tis conceived that every other County which shall henceforth proceed in that path of Honouring those <hi>Sons of Beliall</hi> (for so Scripture calleth such men) by petitioning to them, who have thus disclaimed to Treat with the Annoynted of God, shall be made to drink of that cup, (if they take not warning by others harmes) and to tast deeply of Gods displeasure. Nor must the City of <hi>London</hi> fancy that God will forget her, for her being stil a guard to these evil men, &amp; for affording them the protection of her Trainbands after she had hear'd proclaimed in her streets, <hi>no more Addresses to Gods Vice-gerent:</hi> For 'tis concluded certainly, by the most knowing men, that the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> by that act of theirs, (in disclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Treaty with His Sacred Majesty) have not only renounced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Parliament men,</hi> and (as much as in them lieth) dissolved their own Assembly, <hi>ipso facto,</hi> but also offered the highest contempt and scorne unto the Almighty God (whose Image and Minister the King is) that ever was yet 'offered by mortall creatures; never was such a thing head of in <hi>Israell,</hi> nor amongst the <hi>Heathens;</hi> no story can parallel the same, that of <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abriam</hi> (who said <hi>we will not come up,</hi> when <hi>Moses</hi> sent for them) comes neerest to it, but 'tis not half so black. Indeed Christianity stands amazed at it, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion is ashamed and confounded in her self, that any who pretend to her, should be justly taxable of such a damnable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, which Satan himself upon so evident a proof can scarcely be challenged to be guilty of. Surely that God, who said to <hi>Samuell</hi> (upon a far lesse provocation) <hi>they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me,</hi> will never endure this at the hands of these men; nor will he be pleased with those, who by any further application shall seeme
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161995:10"/>still to approve of them. He expects (undoubtedly) that all people should separate from their society and neighbourhood, (as they of old upon his command, did from <hi>the Tents of Corah</hi> and his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.) For, neither shall these <hi>die the common death of all men,</hi> some <hi>now<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing</hi> rather <hi>will God make,</hi> some remarkable Judgement will he create for this new and unheard of Sin: and 'tis believed, that he had so done ere this, had not his infinite mercies towards some of better conditions, (who through inconsideration of the immensity of the sin, and so of the danger of his high displeasure for it, do yet abide with them, or neere unto them) prevented or suspended the same: God said once, <hi>he could not doe any thing against</hi> Sodome, <hi>till</hi> Lot <hi>was removed thence;</hi> but <hi>Lot</hi> was thereupon <hi>to make hast, and get quick-away;</hi> or else (after warning given, had he stayed) he might have been over-taken: so no doubt but God having some, even in the <hi>Babell</hi> at <hi>Westminster,</hi> whom he loves, who have not concurred in those impious Votes, (of no further Addresses to that Sacred Person, whom by holy Writ they are so expresly bound to Honour) for their sakes hath hitherto forborne to empty forth the viall of his just dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure; and the prayers of good people for them are, that they may not provoke God by too long a stay, least they prove partakers in the end of the judgement: But 'tis firmly believed, that when these have withdrawne themselves, and the City their guards; then, then shall the great wrath of the most Mighty god come downe upon those <hi>men of Beliall,</hi> those <hi>Children of disobedience,</hi> and that in so visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and terrible a manner, that all the world shall see, and say, <hi>'tis the Lords owne doing, verily it is God that judgeth the Earth.</hi> Sir, this is the judgement of many men who are not only discreet and wise, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so (I dare say) of Gods great acquaintance.</p>
            <p>Sir, I hope my desires to Answer yours, shall with your goodnesse excuse the tediousnesse of this discourse. I presume shortly we shall understand more of <hi>Essex</hi> Affaires, and I expect to hear much of God in the management of that businesse in <hi>Colchester.</hi> 'Tis reported that <hi>Suffolke</hi> men have taken great paines in assisting their Enemies to destroy their friends: God hath raised up deliverers for them, but they will none of them; they are willing (it seemes) to lie still under their burdens of oppression and wrong: but <hi>this their way is their folly;</hi> and this their folly hath cost them many of their lives already; though indeed (tis beleeved) that those of <hi>Suffolke</hi> are, and have been only Sectaries, or such as are brought in to aide Generall <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:161995:10"/>by the instigation &amp; compulsion of <hi>Committee-men, Sequestrators,</hi> and <hi>intruding Priests:</hi> for these Wars on that side (in very deed) are only to maintain their Kingdom and Authority: When the full rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole matter shall arrive (if you have it not from a better hand) I shall impart it to you. What I have writ now, I conceive is the truth but I confesse 'tis from the mouths &amp; judgements of other men; wherefore if time, or other information shall fortune to speak any thing to be otherwise; be pleased (I pray) to pardon the unwilling and unwitting Errours of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obliged Friend, and Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAgo 3. line 27. read <hi>Injustice.</hi> pag. 5. l. 17. r. <hi>they must.</hi> l. 20. r <hi>tune.</hi> p. 13. l. 15. r. <hi>their.</hi> p. 14. l. 25. r. <hi>offended.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>